Today's lecture is on central banks.
We already had a few lectures ago about banks.
So what are central banks?
Well, today they're very special government banks that
are responsible for the currency, the money.
And so every country in the
world has a paper money that
has the name of their central bank on it.
But I wanted to take the,
as you know, I like to understand
origins of things, and I wanted
to take it back to the
beginnings of central banking, so we'll understand better
what the institution is.
And I wanted to bring up
first the theme of this course,
which is that financial innovation or invention is an
important thing.
It's a very important thing.
It's a very important process that is not unlike
engineering invention.
When somebody gets an idea and
it's proven to work, it gets
copied all over the world.
That's the way the human species is.
We all have the same kind
of cars, we all have the same
kind of airplanes.
Why?
Not because we're copycats, but because someone has figured
out something that works.
And of course, everyone copies it.
And I think the same
thing is true with central banks.
They're not just a little piece of paper.
They're a little piece of paper.
So, I wanted to get to
the history of central banks and
to go back first to the first central bank.
Then I'll bring it all the
way up to the modern times, where
the recent financial crisis, the actions during the crisis,
the actions of the world's central banks, was extremely
important in preventing what might have been another Great
Depression.
So, these institutions have become a fundamental
part of the world's central banks.
And they're not just a little piece of paper.
They're a whole bunch of little pieces of paper.
So, we're going to go
back to the central banks and
the central banks and the central banks.
And I'll show you some of the most important things
that we can learn in the future.
So, remember the story I
told you in our banking lecture
about how banks got started in the UK.
They'd already been seen earlier in other places, but
the really modern banking institution is traced to the
goldsmith bankers.
So, you'd go to the goldsmith's closet at the
goldsmith banker, and the goldsmith banker would give
you a little piece of paper indicating that you could
anytime come back to the goldsmith and claim this
amount of gold.
And then the pieces of paper started circulating as paper
money.
And that's how it all started.
Unregulated, nothing to do with the government.
It was just private businesses.
And that system, paper money backed
by gold, was a kind of
a system that was a little
bit more complex than the gold
smith bankers.
And it lasted until the 1970s.
Amazing.
Well, it wasn't always gold.
It was bimetallic.
There would be gold and silver, or all silver.
It's a long story.
But we were effectively on the
gold standard until just a few
decades ago.
But there were problems right from the beginning.
And the problem was that sometimes the goldsmith
bankers wouldn't make good on their pledge to redeem and
claim the gold.
You'd come with your piece
of paper, and they'd say, I've
gotten too many requests.
I don't have any gold anymore.
So, that was the problem.
So, I wanted to start with
the Bank of England, which was
founded in 1694.
And it was just a bank.
But it had a special charter.
It was a bank that was
a monopoly on joint stock banking
from the British government that gave it a monopoly on
joint stock banking to start with.
It would be the only bank
in the United Kingdom that was
allowed to issue shares and
sell shares to a large number
of people.
There were other banks, but they were partnerships, and it
had only a limited number of partners.
So, they didn't get as big.
They had only a small number of people.
So, they were a very, very big bank.
And they had a lot of money.
They had a lot of money.
And the Bank of England, which
was the only bank in the
United Kingdom, started a practice.
And this is very important, historically.
It realized it had a lot
of power, because it was the
gorilla bank, and there were a lot of little banks.
And they realized soon that
they could put any bank they
wanted out of business, whenever they felt like it.
How?
They could just present them all for payment.
And no bank could withstand that.
They didn't have enough gold on hand.
So, they could drive any bank to bankruptcy.
But the Bank of England
began to assume its role as
essentially a government bank, without being officially
government, by using a let's
live and let live policy under
one condition.
If you are another bank in the
UK, you have to keep a deposit
with us.
Okay?
And the Bank of England would tell you,
how much.
If you didn't do that, you could be destroyed.
But that created a stability
to the system, because the Bank
of England had money to
bail them out whenever they, you
know, they had a deposit with the Bank of England.
The Bank of England required that.
And so, whenever a bank got
in trouble, they could always take
their money out of the Bank of England.
So, the Bank of England
then would help these banks in
return for their keeping a deposit, sometimes even lend
more money to them.
So, that created a stable banking system over the centuries.
So, that was the model for all
of the central banks of the world.
They're all copies of the Bank of England.
The Bank of England, by
the way, was not an independent.
It became a government bank.
I don't know the whole
history, but it wasn't really independent
of the government until 1997,
when the United Kingdom made it
formally independent.
But nonetheless, it was a bank.
But nonetheless, it was a model for central banking.
And it was observed over much of the world.
Notably, in the United States,
there was a bank called the
Suffolk Bank.
This is much later.
It was founded in 1819 in Boston.
And it was a private bank.
And on its own, it just decided to do the
same thing that the Bank of England did.
It required that all of
the New England banks kept a
deposit with it.
And it did the same thing.
And it stabilized New England from bank runs.
And it lasted, the Suffolk system lasted until 1860.
So, you can see how central banks' inventions of people,
they weren't government inventions at all.
The Suffolk Bank just did this.
It became a big and influential bank.
And the United States in the
early, the first half of the
19th century, had repeated banking crises.
And there were repeated problems with the currency.
It used to be that if you
went to a store, and you wanted to
buy something, they'd say, let's see your money.
You'd take out all of your
money, you'd lay it down, and
they'd look at it.
And they'd say, well, this is
Boston money, this is New Haven
money, this is Hartford money.
And they would pull out a
book called The Bank Note Reporter.
And they'd say, well, our
money dealers are now doing a
20% discount on Hartford money.
So, I'll give you 80 cents
on the dollar for the Hartford
money.
Boston money, we're down 30% on that.
What a messy system.
I shouldn't mention Boston, because Boston had a good
record because of the Suffolk Bank.
So, that's it.
It was worse in other states.
Further, you got from Boston.
So, the Suffolk Bank became held
up as a model of a banking
system.
But the U.S. also had two banks.
One called the Bank of the United States, which was
founded in, I'm forgetting the
year, it's not in my notes.
Anyone tell me, when was
the Bank of the United States
founded?
1789, I think.
And then we had a
second Bank of the United States.
But they weren't really functioning like the Bank of
England.
They were maybe somewhat like
them, but the banks of the
United States were not really central banks, and they were
not renewed.
They disappeared in 1836.
But the big movement in the
United States, there was a lot
of, because the United States didn't want the government
involved in private business.
So, they were reluctant to set
up a central bank for a long
time.
In 1863, the U.S. passed the National Banking Act.
Actually, there was a revision of it in 1864.
And they tried to get some
of the advantages of these central
banks without actually founding one.
And what they did then, is
they said, there's a new kind
of bank called a national bank.
And the national bank would
have a name, like the First
National Bank of New Haven.
Every city created a bank
in 1863, which was called the
First National Bank of something.
And the government required that they keep on deposit with
the treasury capital to back their currency.
So, they were called national bank notes, that were issued
by the banks, printed by the government.
And they all looked the
same, except they had a different
name of the different bank on them.
And they had capital requirements.
So, the banks had to put deposits with the treasury
backing their currency.
And that was a success.
The United States never again had a national bank.
The United States never again
had a problem with its paper
money.
There was never a problem of discounts anymore.
All the national banks would honor each other's notes at
par.
And so, that's when the United
States had a paper money for
the first time.
But it didn't create a system of stable currency.
There were still banking crises, but they had a
different form.
It wasn't a failure of the bank notes.
We fixed the bank note problem in 1863.
But the problem was, there were still runs on banks.
And there were still credit expansions and contractions
that led eventually to people in the United States thinking,
we've got to eventually copy the
Bank of England and do the
same thing here.
And so, there was a
terrible banking crisis in 1893, for
example, when everybody thought the
banks were going to fail.
Somehow, they didn't worry about the currency.
The national bank notes were thought to be perfectly safe.
But they thought the banks weren't
safe, and so there was a
crisis.
And it led to the Depression of the 1890s.
And then there was another one
in 1907 that was really bad.
And so, people wanted to fix somehow the system.
And so, that led to
our current system, which has been
around almost 100 years.
And I call it a copy of
the Bank of England, but it might
not be described that way by everyone.
And it's called the Federal Reserve System.
All right.
And that was created by
an act of Congress in 1913.
And it opened its doors in 1914.
But the U.S., again, we always feel that we're different.
We have to make it look different.
We can't just copy the Bank of England.
We've got to do something different.
So, they said, why don't we create 12 banks?
That sounds more American.
And have them all over the country.
And so, we didn't create a central bank.
We have a banking system with 12 Federal Reserve banks.
But, of course, they decided to
have a headquarters in Washington, D.C.,
called the Federal Reserve Bank.
And the Federal Reserve Bank is
a board, OK, or the board of
governors of the Federal Reserve System is an agency in
Washington that oversees the 12 regional banks.
Do you know what region,
which, the country is divided up.
What region are we in?
It's Boston.
This is the Boston region.
So, most of the money
in your pocket is Boston money.
It only says so now.
It only says so now
on the $1 bills, I think.
But you can look and
see whether, where your money came
from, which of the 12 banks are your currency.
But the Federal Reserve System,
as founded in 1913, required,
just like the Bank of
England, that banks have deposits, or
either currency in their vault, or deposits.
With their Federal Reserve Bank to back up their currency.
And once again, if they
got into trouble, they could draw
on their deposits with the Federal Reserve.
Or, even beyond that, the Federal Reserve could come to
their rescue.
They've been good banks.
They've kept their deposits, just like under the
Suffolk system.
They've kept their deposits with the Federal Reserve.
And so, the Federal Reserve was
going to help them a little
bit more.
And so, it became known
as the Lender of Last Resort.
And the system also operated something called the Discount
Window.
And it was a little bit more complicated than that.
But it was a little bit more complicated than that.
Why do they call it a window?
You people never go into a bank anymore, right?
Do you go into banks?
Remember, they used to have a teller.
And the teller would be sitting
at a sort of a table, and
there was a little something.
He's talking to you through a window.
I guess they wanted to
keep you separate from the money.
So, there was a window where
a teller would talk to you.
And the teller would tell
you, well, the discount window was
a special window at the Federal
Reserve Bank for banks to come.
Just like every, this is the metaphor anyway.
I don't know if they ever had such a window.
And so, the bank that was
in trouble could go to the
discount window and it has to bring something, though.
They have to bring some securities as collateral.
And so, the teller behind the discount window would discount
the collateral brought by the bank and lend money.
So, it's called a discount window because you couldn't
just borrow money.
You had to bring some
asset as collateral for the loan.
And so, in 1913, when the Federal Reserve was founded,
President Wilson, who was president, who signed the bill,
was almost ecstatic.
I have a quote from that.
I don't remember exactly, but something like, we have put
banking crises behind us forever.
And this will lead to a
system of prosperity and I can't think
of all the nice words he used.
People thought that now that
we have adopted the British system,
it ought to be smooth and just like in Britain.
There shouldn't be a problem anymore.
And so, we still live with that system today.
I think Wilson was right.
It was a big step forward.
And again, it was a copying of other people's successes.
Nobody knows exactly how the banking system worked.
There's a theory of money and
banking, but it has worked in
practice.
And so, central bankers start to become very important in
modern society.
Because they are really the
keepers of the gate, of the
sensible lending.
There is a tendency for banking
systems to over lend, to create
booms, and create a false prosperity for a while, and
then it crashes.
And we have a banking panic
and a recession or a depression.
So,
that means then, the banking system
has to be the source of
stability and good sense.
We tend to recruit as
central bankers, people who are moral
and stable in their lives.
One of our Federal Reserve chairs, William McChesney
Martin, said, summed it up very
nicely, the job of the central
banker is to take away the
punch bowl as soon as possible.
The punch bowl is to take away
the punch bowl as soon as the
party gets going.
It's like a parent, right?
Taking away, you can have one
drink, but we're going to stop.
And so, that's what the central bank.
The central bank controls the system through reserve
requirements.
That is, by telling the banks,
who are members of the system,
who hold the money, who are
the people, who hold the money,
who hold the money.
And then they have to make
sure that the bank is the only
bank that can hold in
reserves, which are deposits at the
central bank, or currency.
If they hold currency in
their vault, if it's right there,
then they're okay.
This term, reserve requirement, actually
goes back to before the
Federal Reserve, because we had
state, in the United States, we
had state banking regulators that were already imposing
the Federal Reserve in the 1900s
in the United States, during the
Progressive Era.
And so, there are also capital requirements.
And I'll come back to
making a distinction between the two.
Capital requirements and reserve requirements, both of
them, flourished around 1900,
even before the Federal Reserve,
with state banking regulators
who were requiring both capital
and reserves in the United States.
I don't know the history of every other country.
But after the Federal Reserve was
set up in 1913, it began to
take over both of these functions of setting reserve
requirements and setting capital requirements.
So, that's the Federal Reserve.
Thank you.
Let me go a little forward in history.
The system appeared great.
We had the Federal Reserve.
We had, now, every country of
the world, not just the U.S.
and the U.K., virtually every
country of the world had a
central bank.
Even communist countries, I think, had central banks.
But the system broke down in 1933.
Actually, before 1933, after 1929, banks started to fail.
And the Federal Reserve could have bailed out the banks.
In the United States, they
started to fail, not the United
Kingdom.
But there was a banking crisis
after 1929, and it reached its
peak in 1930.
And the bank was shut down in 1933.
So, just before President Roosevelt took office, the banks
were in total disarray.
And the first thing Roosevelt
did as President was to shut
down the entire banking system of the United States.
It was called the banking holiday, because everyone was
running to the bank.
It was a catastrophic bank run.
And it was quite a scary situation, because nobody could
get their money.
The banks were all closed, all of them.
And people started to run out of money.
I remember, was it the Harvard
Crimson did a poll of its
students, asking them, how much
money do you have in your
pocket?
And it got down to,
like, 10 cents and 5 cents.
They just spent all their money.
And they said, well, you can do.
I mean, how can you get lunch?
Well, I assume they had a cafeteria.
Somehow, you could still do it.
You couldn't go anywhere and
spend any money if you didn't
have it, because it was all tied up.
So, people started changing IOUs,
and it was just a mess.
So, the Federal Reserve didn't stop that crisis.
But the Roosevelt administration, the
Roosevelt administration did other things to prevent crises
like this.
Notably, set up the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.
Now, this was a, deposit insurance had preceded the
FDIC in 1933, but it had never been a success.
It had been tried in a number of places.
The U.S., I think, set the example for deposit insurance
in 1937.
And that began to augment central banking.
The U.S. had not had another banking crisis since 1933,
until 2007, just recently.
Well, I should say, there was
the saving and loan crisis, but
not a big banking crisis.
And that is testimony to, I think, the importance of
the Federal Reserve.
But the Federal Reserve began to
see its role as not so much
preventing banking crises, that
was always in the background,
but as stabilizing the economy.
And so, the Fed began to
think of itself as preventing the
recurrence of recessions.
So, when the economy was overheating, the inflation was
building up, the Fed would
raise interest rates, and the higher
interest rates would cool down the economy.
And when the economy got too soft, when the unemployment
rate went up, the Fed would
cut interest rates, and that would
encourage borrowing, encourage spending,
and boost the economy.
Actually, that function of the
Fed goes back even before 1933.
And there was an economist,
Charles Amos Dice, who wrote in
the 1920s that the Federal Reserve is like the regulator
on a steam engine.
Do you know anything about steam engines?
They have this thing that whirls around with two little
weights, and if the steam
engine gets too fast, the weight
spins out by centrifugal force, and
it cuts off the steam, so
that it doesn't overheat.
The engine doesn't get going too fast.
And so, Dice said, the Federal Reserve is an invention.
Now, that is serving a different, it's the regulator
for the whole economy.
And I think he was
right, although it's not as accurate
as a regulator on a
steam engine, but it works somewhat
well.
I wanted to mention, every
country now has a central bank,
but I just wanted to mention the European Central Bank,
because it's quite new, and it's maybe the biggest central
bank now, in the sense that
it, well, I shouldn't say that.
It might be the biggest central bank by some standard.
There was a treaty signed at
Maastricht in 1992, which was a
treaty that was signed by
the European Union, which led to
the creation of the European Union from the European
Communities, and it also created a plan for a new
currency called the Euro, which is a European currency.
And the Euro did not
actually start until 1999, and the
currency, actual currency, was not issued until 1999.
So, that is a relatively recent invention.
The European Central Bank, or ECB, was founded in 1998.
That's before the Euro currency started.
They created a list of countries
that wanted to participate in the
Euro zone.
The Euro zone, not all European Union countries decided to
participate in the Euro.
Notably, the United Kingdom had
a referendum and voted against
it, and to this day, they
are not members of the Euro.
Also, Sweden, Lithuania, Latvia, Estonia, Poland, Czech
Republic, Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria, and Malta are not in
the Euro zone.
Some of these countries that
are not officially in the Euro
zone use the Euro unofficially.
It's not their currency, but there's no law against Euro
coming in and spending Euros.
So, the Euro seems more distributed than that.
So, anyway, that's the most recent central bank.
But it's the same general structure.
Every European country has its own central bank.
It's the same general structure.
Every European country has its own central bank, like the
Banca d'Italia or the Deutsche Bundesbank.
But their original purpose is
kind of gone, because they no
longer maintain a currency.
There are no more Deutschmarks or Italian Lira.
They're all using the Euro.
So, the real central bank
is the European Central Bank in
Frankfurt, led by Jean-Claude Trichet right now.
So, that's the real central bank.
Bank of Japan, by the way, became independent.
I mentioned that in 1997.
Bank of Japan, another very important central bank.
There's been a movement in
the last few decades to make
central banks independent.
This was something that our own Federal Reserve had from
the beginning.
The Federal Reserve was designed to be separate from
the government.
The reason was, they thought that a government might want
to inflate the currency.
Political pressures might, at certain times, cause them to
try to influence the central bank.
And so, the Federal Reserve was
set up so that the members
of the Board of Governors had 14-year terms.
They couldn't be kicked out, except for impeachment
offenses.
And so, the government couldn't control the central bank.
The independent central bank has been very important.
What tends to happen is, you
bring people in who've had long
careers in banking, who have a reputation for integrity, and
you tell them that you
are the custodian of the currency.
You bring in people who believe
in the importance of a stable
currency, and then you give
them a 14-year term, and they're
there.
It's like the Supreme Court, almost.
You can't kick them out.
And some people think that's why
the U.S. has had such a
stable price level, because of our independent central bank.
So many countries have fallen into inflation that has
undermined the currency, but the U.S. hasn't.
I think that's why there has
been a move to copy the
independent central bank.
I wanted to talk now
about specifics of what the central
bank does.
Notably, the Federal Reserve System has a committee called
the Federal Open Markets Committee, FOMC, Federal Open
Markets Committee, that meets around once a month.
And they issue a statement.
Every time they meet.
And as it is now, actually,
FOMC doesn't go back to 1913,
but I'm talking about the
Federal Reserve as it is now.
This committee decides on a range for an interest rate
called the Federal Funds Rate.
And the Federal Funds Rate is an overarching interest rate.
So, if you have an
overnight interest rate that is charged
on loans between banks
and some other financial institutions,
you generally would not have access to the Federal Funds
Rate.
Now, you probably don't need
it, because you don't need an
overnight loan anyway, right?
Most of us would borrow
money for more than one night.
But banks, for various reasons,
do this lending and borrowing
in a day, at least under normal circumstances.
So, we have an overnight interest rate.
There's also longer federal funds, but we're emphasizing
the overnight rate.
And it's unsecured.
This is just an unsecured, there's no collateral.
It's an unsecured loan between banks.
So, the interest rate reflects some risk, negligible risk,
usually.
And the interest rate is not unsecured, because banks trust
each other, at least overnight.
They know pretty much they're going to get paid back.
And the current Federal Funds
Rate in the United States is
0.13%, as of last Friday.
That's 13 basis points.
So, it's virtually zero.
This is a policy decision of the Federal Open Markets
Committee.
They have decided that the
range for the Federal Funds Rate
should be between 0 and 25 basis points.
So, as of last Friday, it
was exactly in the middle of their
range.
The FOMC uses its decisions to
set the Federal Funds Rate as a
way of stabilizing the economy.
This is the regulator that Dice talked about.
Right now, they've set it virtually at zero, because the
economy is so weak.
The unemployment rate last week was 8.8%, extremely high.
And so, the Federal Reserve
is not worried about inflation now.
It's worried about high unemployment.
And it's pushed it about as close
to zero as it can get it.
It can't go below zero,
because you can't have negative interest
rates.
No one would lend at a negative interest rate.
So, that's where we are.
Now, I wanted to just
tell you about an interesting development
that came in just in 2008.
I mentioned that banks hold reserves.
And the reason why banks
hold reserves is because they have
a very strong interest rate.
And the reason why banks
hold reserves is because they have
a very strong interest rate.
And the reason why banks
hold reserve accounts at the Federal
Reserve, traditionally, those accounts were not interest
paying.
I mean, banks had to either
hold money or an account at the
Federal Reserve for their reserves.
And neither of them pay interest, right?
If you hold money, you don't get any interest.
If you actually have currency
in your vault, you don't get
interest.
And until recently, banks didn't get interest on the
interest rate.
They didn't get interest on their deposits at the Federal
Reserve.
But that all changed in 2008 with the Emergency Economic
Stabilization Act that President George Bush signed,
ESA, as it's called.
And ESA allowed the Federal
Reserve to pay interest on the
reserves held in the accounts at the Federal Reserve.
So, the Federal Reserve has
a policy now of paying interest
on reserve balances.
You see what I'm saying?
I don't know what the Suffolk
Bank did or the Bank of England
did, but I know what
the Federal Reserve is doing now.
If a member bank puts
money in deposit with the Federal
Reserve, they will get an interest rate.
And you can find out what
the interest rate is by going to
the Federal Reserve website.
And right now, it is 0.25%.
That's it.
And so, that's an important policy change, because now it
encourages the holding of reserves.
Now, some people look at this and ask this question.
Here's the Federal funds rate.
Why isn't it the same as the interest on reserves?
Interesting question.
Why would any bank invest
in the Federal funds market if
they can get a higher interest
rate by just holding a reserve
at the Federal Reserve?
There's been a lot of
discussion of why that is now.
It's a new phenomenon, because the interest on reserves goes
back only less than three years.
I think the simplest answer to
the question is, why is it so?
The first answer to the question
is that member banks of the Federal
Reserve System have stopped lending on the Federal funds
market, basically.
They just leave it in
reserves, because that's a higher interest
rate.
So, who is lending at this?
It turns out that there
are some people, notably the government
sponsored enterprises, like Fannie and Freddie, that are not
eligible for interest on reserves.
So, they have taken over the Federal funds market.
The reason the Fed added interest
on reserves is to create another
tool of monetary policy.
There's a lot of concern that after
this crisis is over, there will be
a sudden surge of inflation.
And let me come back to that.
Basically, what the Fed has a new
tool is, if that happens to raise the
interest on reserves, and that
will help contract the economy
instantly, very rapidly.
The way the Fed controls the
Federal funds rate, and has been doing
for years, is by buying and
selling Treasury bills on the open market,
by affecting the supply and demand for short-term credit.
And that indirectly, they don't
actually deal in the Federal funds
market.
They deal in the Treasury bill market.
But since those markets are interlinked, they indirectly
target the Federal funds rate.
So, that's the old way
of trading in the Federal funds
market, not in the Federal
funds market, trading in the short-term
Treasury market through the New York Fed.
But now they have a new tool.
So, we're entering a whole new regime of monetary policy.
Okay.
So, I wanted to talk about
reserve requirements a little bit more,
and what those are.
So, the Federal Reserve has the
authority to set the amount of reserves
that a bank holds.
I wanted to make clear
the distinction between a reserve requirement
and capital requirements.
So, okay, the Federal Reserve
has what's called Regulation D,
which specifies how much banks have to
hold as a function of their liabilities.
And as of right now, the
reserve requirements are 10% of transaction accounts.
Okay, that means that a bank has to
total up all of the transaction accounts, and that
consists of checking accounts.
What are the now accounts and ATS accounts.
Transactions accounts are accounts like checks that
people have a deposit in the bank that
they'll use for spending.
And those are instantly withdrawable.
Okay.
In contrast, there's something called time deposits.
Those are savings accounts.
And the bank does not have
to give you the money immediately.
In other words, if you go
to your checking account and say,
I want my money, it's a transaction account,
they have to give it to you instantly.
That's the rule.
But if you go to your saving
account, they can stall, because it's a,
you might not have noticed it,
but it's in the fine print somewhere.
This is a time deposit.
So, the Fed is not worried about time deposits.
Here, we're talking about reserve requirements.
Reserve requirements are still based on the
old theory that we're trying to prevent bank
runs.
Okay?
And so, we don't want people to, we don't
want there to be a run on banks, where people
panic and try to withdraw their money all at once.
So, we want to make
sure that banks have enough reserves.
And the Fed currently thinks 10% ought to be enough.
For time deposits, it's zero.
You don't have to put any
money on reserve for time deposits.
Why does the Fed think that?
Because you've got 60, 90 days or
a year to pay the person back.
So, they can't run on you.
So, we don't require any
reserve requirements against time deposits.
But it's 10% for transactions account, which
is substantial, because they're still worried about this.
Okay.
So, this is the situation.
We used to talk, emphasize in lectures
about central banking, the so-called money multiplier.
Okay?
The money multiplier, well, it's complicated, but
the simplest thing is, it might be one
over the reserve requirement.
It's not exactly that, but if the
reserve requirement is 10%, then the total amount
of deposits that banks can issue
is one over the reserve requirement.
Okay?
So, the total amount of deposits that banks can
issue is going to be 10 times the amount
of currency and deposits they have at the Federal Reserve.
So, that means the reserve requirements would
fix the money supply under the old theory.
Because, you know, the high-powered money is
the currency plus deposits at the Federal Reserve.
That's reserves.
And if the reserve requirement is 10%,
and banks want to just meet the requirements,
and nothing more, they're going to have 10
times as much deposits, right, as there are reserves.
I'm oversimplifying the money multiplier.
But I'm telling you that at the
moment in history, it's irrelevant, because banks are
holding excess reserves.
The world has changed.
Just a few years ago, before this financial
crisis, banks didn't want to hold excess reserves.
And so, there were hardly any excess reserves.
Why?
Because they don't get any interest on them, all right?
And so, banks didn't hold excess reserves.
So, the money market multiplier theory would
work, because the amount of reserve was just
about exactly equal to 10% of transactions.
I'm oversimplifying, but something like that was true.
But now, they're paying 25 basis points on reserves.
So, that's a lot more than you
can get investing in the Federal Funds Market.
And banks are just perfectly happy to hold excess reserves.
So, the excess reserves now are
over, I think it's 1.2 trillion.
It's huge, because of interest on reserves.
I don't have the exact number, but something
has fundamentally changed in just the last few years.
So, reserve requirements, they must hold for some banks.
But for most banks, they don't
even look at reserve requirements anymore.
What do I care?
I'm so happy to hold reserves.
I'll hold way more than they require.
So, reserve requirements are non-binding for most banks now.
So, it's a different world.
This brings us then to capital requirements.
Capital requirements.
So, in the world, history has always changed.
The world, as of a few
years ago, everyone emphasized reserve requirements.
And those were the requirements that
had as its motive preventing bank runs.
But we're not going to have a bank run now,
when these banks have over a trillion dollars just sitting there.
They're holding so much.
It's not an issue right now.
So, something else has taken the center stage.
And that is capital requirements,
which we talked about last time.
So, capital requirements are
different from reserve requirements.
I just defined, reserve requirements were
a fraction of the transaction accounts.
They were defined by a liability.
A transaction account is like a checking account.
It's some money that the bank owes to other people.
And we have this requirement that
10% of that is the reserve requirement.
But capital requirements are different.
And they're more likely to be binding these days.
And these were emphasized in Basel
III, which we talked about before.
So, it's a different thing.
And it's a different thing
than what we talked about before.
So, Basel III is not yet in force.
It's going to take a long time.
Basel III has a phase-in period that is
going to take until, I think, it's 2019.
But there's a lot of talk now
about trying to get Basel III phased in.
So, remember, we talked about risk-weighted assets.
Now it is banks have to hold
capital as a fraction of their risk-weighted assets.
So, right now, the countries of the world, they've agreed.
The G20 countries have agreed on Basel III.
But each country has to decide
on the implementation of Basel III.
The United States, in particular,
is having problems with Basel III,
because Basel III refers to credit ratings in many places.
But Dodd-Frank, the Dodd-Frank Act, Act of 2010,
abolishes credit ratings.
The government will no longer make any
use in any regulation of credit ratings.
Remember what credit ratings are.
Moody's and Standard & Poor's are
the two best-known credit rating agencies.
The government, the SEC, starting in 1975,
defined what they called NRA.
N-R-S-R-O's.
That's Nationally Recognized
Statistical Rating Organization.
All right?
And that included Moody's, which was founded in about 1900,
and Standard & Poor's, which was
a result of the merger of
Standard Statistical Association and Poor's,
a little bit after 1900.
They're venerable old institutions that
give a risk rating for securities.
For example, Moody's will give its
best securities a triple A rating.
Okay?
That means Moody's thinks they'll never default.
Yale University is rated triple A by Moody's, for example.
But they go, if they don't like you
quite as much, they'll downrate you to double A.
Or if they don't like
you even more, you're only A.
And then, God forbid, you go down into the B's.
It's like, in fact, Moody, John Moody
in his book acknowledges that it was just,
he took the same grading
system that he got in college.
I don't know why, it's a little different.
You don't get a triple A grade here, do you?
I've never given a triple A.
But that's how Moody saw it.
And so, it's like letter grades to securities.
Well, Moody did that in 1900.
And if you read his
autobiography, people said, you're crazy.
How can you give a grade to a security?
It seemed like a wild idea.
But he stuck with it.
And over the years, people began
to believe in them more and more.
So, it led to an idea that
we fully understand the risk of securities.
And so, there was a
set of, a complacency set in.
And the government started,
to recognize these NRSROs as if
they were proclaimers of God's truth.
And they started all kinds of regulations,
said what your capital had to be,
depending on the rating of various assets you hold.
But the whole thing collapsed
in the recent financial crisis,
because some triple A securities lost almost everything.
So, the rating agencies made a big problem, issue.
And so, Congress,
has now said, nobody can make any
regulation based on ratings of the NRSROs.
But Basel III people didn't get the message.
Well, they're not America, they're international.
And they still believe in them.
I think it's a little bit
difficult to know how to handle risk.
This is the fundamental problem.
And it would be nice if
Moody's and S&P could tell us.
But the problem is that they missed this whole crisis.
They didn't see it coming.
And why didn't they?
Well, that's a deep issue.
That's what people are wrestling with right now.
So, the U.S. has to figure out what to do,
to reinterpret the Basel III
recommendations for the United States,
without using any reference to Moody's and S&P.
What will probably happen, I think,
is that the banks will have
to have their own risk committees,
and they will have to come up with a plan,
and they will have to come
up with their own assessments of risk,
and they'll be responsible for those.
But what will really happen is,
they'll just look at the Moody's and S&P ratings,
and it'll be rubber stamping them.
So, I don't think that, there's a whole question,
whether Dodd-Frank will be
effective in reducing our requirement.
But I wanted to go
over the capital requirements once again,
because now they're increasingly important.
And I wanted to go through,
just a simple example of capital requirements,
so that you'll understand them.
And I don't think the general
public understands them very well at all.
Okay.
And so, this is old accounting, or old finance.
These requirements go back 100 years.
I'm going to talk in very simple terms about them.
I'm not going to go over-simplifying.
Basel III is a complicated new agreement.
It has a lot of ins and outs.
But I'm just going to over-simplify it,
and talk about the Basel III common equity requirements.
I'm going to tell a
little story about founding a bank.
And let's just understand how capital requirements work.
So, imagine that you decided to found a bank.
And in developed countries of the world today,
you can do this.
You can set up your own bank.
The only problem you have,
you have to get a charter.
You have to apply for a charter.
You have to decide whether you're
a national bank in the United States,
or some other kind of bank.
But you get a charter, and you open your doors.
Now, you've got to
start complying with capital requirements.
But let's say you do that, all right?
You find that there's an empty bank building downtown.
All right?
So, you go through the paperwork,
and you set up your bank,
and you open the doors.
And now, we have one
of those windows with a teller,
and inviting deposits, okay?
So, I'm going to tell a story, which is over-simplified,
and maybe a little bit, let's
say that you open your doors,
and someone walks in with
$100 and deposits it, all right?
So, this is your bank.
Or I'll say, my bank, okay?
All right?
So, you've got a bank.
And the bank has, now, you
probably, I think regulators would require
you come up with some capital first.
But I'm going to tell the story.
It seems to be a nicer story.
You start out with deposit.
Assume your regulators allowed you to start.
So, somebody walks in and deposits.
And here's your assets, and here's your liabilities, okay?
Left side is assets, right side is liabilities.
So, someone deposits $100 in
cash to your bank, all right?
And you've got an asset, now, of $100, okay?
And you have a liability, now, of $100.
If that's a savings account,
you don't have any reserve requirements.
If it's a transactions account, you have to hold $10.
I've got it, right?
I've got $100 sitting in my vault,
because the guy just gave me $100.
So, I'm satisfying both my reserve requirements and my,
now, am I satisfying my capital requirements?
Well, I have to calculate risk-weighted assets, all right?
Remember, every kind of asset has its risk.
What about cash?
Well, cash has a zero risk.
So, it has a zero risk weighting.
So, right now, my risk-weighted assets equals zero, okay?
Now, okay, I've got to satisfy
all the regulations that are on me.
I'm satisfying my reserve requirements, right?
I've got my reserve, I've got $100.
This is cash in my safe.
And this is a liability.
I owe $100 in the form of
a, let's say, it's a transaction account.
Whenever this person comes back,
I've got to pay $100, okay?
All right, so, my reserve requirements are satisfied.
Because I've got more than 10% of my transactions account.
My risk-weighted assets are zero.
Now, Basel III says that you have to
hold 4.5% of your risk-weighted assets as capital.
But now, wait a minute, I have a problem.
What is my capital here?
I don't have any capital.
I've just opened my doors
and I've got $100 in assets.
I've got $100 in liabilities.
Everything looks okay from reserve
requirement, but there's no capital.
So, what is capital?
I have to issue shares to come up with capital.
And I'm going to need 4.5% common equity requirement.
And they also have something called a capital
conservation buffer, which is another 2.5% plus 2.5%,
which you don't absolutely have to hold, but
if you don't hold it, you're subject to restrictions.
So, I'm going to add these.
This is the capital conservation buffer.
I've got to hold 7% under Basel III.
And I don't have any capital here.
All right.
So, what do I do?
I'm not in compliance.
So, I've got to do something.
I've got to raise capital.
So, what I can do is I can issue shares.
I have to find, sell shares in the business.
So, all I need to do is
sell 7, well, okay, what would it be?
Let's say I put in, I issue $20 in shares.
Okay.
And then that means someone gives me more
cash, right, because someone paid for the shares.
So, I've now got $120.
Well, I add another plus 20.
So, it's a total assets
of 120 all held in cash.
Okay.
Now, I've got, now this is
not a different kind of liability.
This is common equity.
And the regulators make a big distinction between this kind of
liability, the transaction account, and this kind of liability, the $20.
Why do they make a big distinction?
Because this guy can come to the window anytime and
you've got to give them $100, whenever this person asks.
The shareholders have no demand on you at all.
They own a share of the company.
You don't, they can't come
to the window and demand anything.
You can just send them away.
The only deal you have with shareholders is that all shareholders will
receive an equal dividend if the board of directors decides to vote dividend.
They're shareholders in the company.
But they can't run the bank.
The shareholders can't show up at the window.
So, there's no risk of bank runs for them.
And there's no risk of problems because if anything goes
bad, you just tell the common equity guys, you're out.
You lost.
Okay.
So, now, what are my risk-weighted assets?
They're still zero.
I've got $120 in cash, zero.
I don't have any, 7% times zero is zero.
So, now, I'm in great shape.
I've satisfied both my reserve requirements and
I've satisfied my Basel III capital requirements.
Okay.
So, what do we do next?
We created a bank.
And there's no interest paid on these two.
And there's no interest paid on these checking accounts.
And we're not earning any interest.
We've got a bank and we're satisfied in the requirements.
But nobody is making any money.
So, we've got to do something to make money.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to, let's say we get our board of directors meeting.
The board of directors is
elected by the common equity shareholders.
And we decide, let's make some corporate loans.
So, why don't we lend out all of this $100 that
was cash and lend it to some business as a corporate loan.
And then we'll charge them interest.
Now, we're going to start making money.
So, this is no longer cash in safe.
This is corporate loans.
Loans to corporations to do business.
All right.
So, there we are.
Our balance sheet balances.
Everything looks fine.
But what is our risk-weighted asset now?
Well, you remember, corporate loans get a 100% risk-weight.
Because under Basel, going back to Basel I,
they always thought corporate loans are risky assets.
So, my risk-weighted assets are now $100.
Okay?
And 7% of $100 is $7.
So, hey, I'm doing fine.
Now, we're capitalized enough.
We're in business.
We're satisfying both our reserve requirements.
Reserve requirements being 10%.
And that's only $12.
And we've got it in cash.
And we're satisfying our Basel III capital requirements.
So, everything is fine.
Everything is fine.
And we're in business.
And we're not done yet.
Because our risk-weighted assets, our
$7 is the capital requirement.
And we've got $20 in common equity.
Okay.
So, everything is great.
This is fine.
But now, let's go on.
Now, there's a crisis.
All right?
Business gets bad.
So, the next thing that happens
is 20% of my corporate loans default.
Okay?
And so, we then, you know, it becomes clear.
We have another board meeting.
And someone says, I have bad news.
We made $100 in corporate loans.
But these guys, $20 is
never going to get paid back.
The borrower is out of business.
So, I suggest we do
a write-off of our corporate loans.
And let's reduce them to $80.
Okay?
So, what happens?
Now, assets have to equal liabilities.
$100 is our assets now, not $120.
Right?
Because we just lost $20.
Our liabilities can't be $120 because
they have to equal our assets.
What gives?
Well, it's the shareholders that give.
So, we mark down common equity to zero.
And now, assets and liabilities match.
So, now, let's look at our requirements.
What about our reserve requirements?
Reserve requirements are fine.
We're holding excess reserves.
You know, we only have to hold $10.
And we've got $20 in cash.
But we're no longer satisfying our capital requirements.
So, our bank regulator is going to show us,
our bank regulator is going to shut us
down unless we do something to raise capital.
So, how do we raise capital?
That's the next step.
Well, one thing we could do is
we could sell some of our corporate loans.
Right?
We could find a buyer for our corporate loans.
And we could sell, say, $20 worth of them.
Bring this down to $60.
And this would go up to $40.
All right?
So, our risk-weighted assets would now –
well, then, let me see.
No, that wouldn't do it.
I'm sorry.
That wouldn't do it, would it?
We'd still have – we
still don't have – I'm sorry.
I misspoke.
We still don't have any common equity.
In this case, if we don't have any common equity,
we can't get out of this by selling our loans.
We could have if it didn't reduce it to zero.
If the common equity went down to $10, then I could
sell some of my corporate loans to get out of this mess.
Right?
But I made it zero.
So, the only way out that I
can do is to issue more shares.
So, I've got to go to my friends again and
say, well, we started this bank, but we goofed up.
We made bad loans.
And so, we've exhausted our common equity.
I've got to raise more capital now.
And so, what you could do
is get more friends to come in.
Now, they might not want to do it,
because the previous friends just got wiped out.
They lost everything, right?
But you're coming in as new
shareholders on top of the old.
And you could then go back to where
you were before by just issuing more shares.
So, this is the system.
I think I've pretty much summarized it.
It's simple.
Now, the issue is, however, that what
motivated Basel III was that the –
this system of requiring banks to hold
capital is supposed to stabilize the system.
If they've got enough common equity, the bank won't go
bankrupt, even if they lose some of their corporate loans.
It would be a big
disaster to drive them to insolvency.
But the problem is that the system they set up
has banks responding to a crisis by selling corporate loans,
or selling – issuing new shares.
The problem is, both of those
are hard to do in a crisis.
In a crisis, you know, and everything
is falling apart, you go out saying,
I want to issue new shares
in my bank that just lost everything.
Investors are going to say, you've got to be kidding.
I'm not going to invest in you right now.
So, you can't raise new equity.
Okay, what about selling loans?
Well, the problem is, in a
big national – or international crisis,
every bank on the planet –
every bank on the planet is trying
to sell its loans at the same time.
So, it creates a collapse in the system.
And this is what happened in the financial crisis.
This story repeated a million times,
was banks were trying to raise capital,
and they were trying to sell assets,
either by issuing – they were trying to raise
capital either by issuing shares or by selling assets.
And everyone doing it at
the same time created a crunch.
And the whole system would have collapsed
if it weren't for the central banks.
And the central banks of the
world responded quickly by loans to companies,
to banks and other companies.
So, the lender of last resort
saved the whole system from collapsing.
That's the story of the financial crisis.
The remaining story is the
Basel III people in Switzerland said,
let's analyze how we got into this situation.
How did it get so bad?
And they thought, you know, it's a big problem.
And it was kind of a funny system, because
we're requiring banks to raise capital at the worst time.
And that can't be the right system.
And they looked around and tried
to decide what to do better.
Most countries of the world
were following this kind of system.
There was some – some people were impressed
by the government of Spain having a better system.
But the Spanish banking system collapsed anyway.
So, it didn't solve the problem.
So, Basel III came up with a
solution, which was to allow the central regulators
to add another buffer of 2.5%.
If they think there's a bubble going on.
They would do this before the crisis.
And that raises the common equity requirement to 9.5%.
So, the idea is, this
is going to be a problem.
Raising capital at a time of difficulty
is always going to be a problem.
And we can always rely again on
our central banks, but maybe we can't.
Maybe we shouldn't.
And so, the idea is,
let's take bank regulators in mind.
Let's take them in mind.
Let's take bank regulators and make it
their obligation to raise capital requirements in advance,
when they see a bubble coming.
Now, another thing that happened in the
United States is the Dodd-Frank Act of 2010.
Because of intense public reaction to all
the bailouts, said that the Federal Reserve
can no longer use discretion in
deciding who's going to be in charge.
They can operate a discount window, but
it has to be completely fair and even.
They can't decide, we're going to bail out Bear
Stearns, and we're going to let Lehman Brothers fail.
All they can do is operate a consistent discount window.
So, the Dodd-Frank Act constrained the
central bank in the United States
from exercising the kind of judgment
that saved us from the crisis.
So, we're going to have to do something about it.
And we're going to have to rely
on some different things, like better capital standards,
like Basel III, to fix the situation.
Whether we're there or not is
going to be a big question.
This is a complicated system, and we put a
lot of the best minds into trying to figure out
how to prevent the kind of
instability that we're seeing in this example,
where everyone is short on capital at the same time,
everyone is selling loans at the
same time, and the whole system collapses.
We've come up with different solutions,
but they have to be implemented yet,
and there are problems of implementation.
The role of central banks and
of regulatory authorities are evolving and changing,
and it'll be a period of many years
before we know where this system is actually going.
All right, I will stop here.
Next lecture is on investment banking,
and we have a former Econ 252 student, Jan Fugner,
who is back after nine years,
and he will tell us about
his experiences as an investment banker,
and also a Facebook executive.